{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This composer incorporated the song \"Bright Sun, You Do Not Shine Equally\" into a piece to raise money for Red Cross agents helping Serbian casualties of an 1876 war with Turkey, his Marche Slave. For 10 points, name this Russian composer who depicted the Battle of Borodino turning back Napoleon from Moscow in his 1812 Overture.",
      "answer": "Pyotr Ilyich Tchaikovsky"
    },
    {
      "question": "A Confederacy of thirteen of these places included eight “city” ones and five “forest” ones. Several of these places fought in the Kappel Wars, and the westernmost ones have been French- speaking for centuries. These places include Uri and Glarus, while in Graubunden, Romansh and German are spoken. For 10 points, name these geographical divisions that make up Switzerland.",
      "answer": "cantons of Switzerland"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man depicted Leutze’s (LOYT-zuh’s) Washington Crossing the Delaware in the background of a satirical portrait of three old women intended to be crossdressed depictions of the Founding Fathers. A painting by this artist shows his dentist and sister as a farming couple. For 10 points, name this Midwestern artist of Daughters of Revolution & American Gothic.",
      "answer": "Grant Wood"
    },
    {
      "question": "A leader of this country's Communist Party wrote the Prison Notebooks and coined the concept of \"hegemony.\" This country was also home to the man whose On Crimes and Punishments founded the field of criminology, and the coiner of the 80-20 rule. For 10 points, name this homeland of Antonio Gramsci (GROM-shee) and Vilfredo Pareto.",
      "answer": "Italy"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man replaced Robert M. La Follette, Jr. in the Senate after a primary campaign in which he accused La Follette of war profiteering. This man was the subject of the \"Declaration of Conscience Speech\" and Joseph Welch's remark that he had \"no sense of decency.\" For 10 points, name this Wisconsin Senator who worked with Roy Cohn to find Communists.",
      "answer": "Joseph McCarthy"
    },
    {
      "question": "The first four holders of this title were called \"rightly-guided\", or rashidun. Two claimants to this title fought at Karbala. A research center called the House of Wisdom was built under a holder of this title named Harun al-Rashid, who ruled from Baghdad. For 10 points, name this Islamic title used by the Umayyads and Abbasids, which means \"successor to the Prophet.\"",
      "answer": "caliphs"
    },
    {
      "question": "A writer from this country denounced a war as \"a fight between two bald men over a comb\" in the poem Juan López y (wahn loh-pez ee) John Ward and described the endless \"Library of Babel.\" For 10 points, name this home country of Jorge Luis Borges (BORE-hays), who condemned its participation in the Falklands War.",
      "answer": "Argentina"
    },
    {
      "question": "One holder of this position was assassinated after going to a railway station to meet Vladimir Kokovstov in retaliation for signing the Eulsa Treaty. Another holder of this position earned the nickname “Razor” while heading the military police in the Kwantung Army, and attempted suicide while awaiting trial before the Tokyo War Crimes Tribunal. For 10 points, name this government position held by Ito Hirobumi and Hideki Tojo.",
      "answer": "Prime Minister of Japan"
    },
    {
      "question": "Fulk III of Anjou built dozens of a type of this structure called a donjon. An early version of this structure featured a motte (MAHT) and a bailey. One type of entrance to these structures was the barbican, which often included a portcullis. These structures centered on a keep and were surrounded by moats. For 10 points, name this type of fortification common in Medieval Europe.",
      "answer": "castles"
    },
    {
      "question": "This law's enforceability was upheld in the Supreme Court case of Ableman v. Booth, which invalided the \"personal liberty laws\" many states passed to undermine it. This law led to a contentious trial in Boston over Anthony Burns. For 10 points, name this portion of the Compromise of 1850 which required northern free states to help recapture escaped slaves.",
      "answer": "Fugitive Slave Act NHBB B 2014-2015"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This animal is believed to give the \"five products\" including gobar, an energy source. The tilak mark is often made from the excrement of these animals, which are the subject of the holiday Gopastami. Killing these animals was prohibited by the Vedas, and they are now a major cause of traffic hindrance in Delhi. For 10 points, name these animals sacred to Hindus.",
        "answer": "cows"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What Hindu destroyer god rides Nandi, the \"bull of heaven?\"",
        "answer": "Shiva"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man responded to Barack Obama's Cairo address with the 2009 \"Bar-Ilan (BAR ee- LAHN) speech.\" He originally became prime minister after defeating Shimon Peres in a 1996 direct election, and has been in office again since forming a coalition against Tzipi Livni's Kadima (kah-DEE-muh) party. For 10 points, name this current prime minister of Israel.",
        "answer": "Benjamin \"Bibi\" Netanyahu"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Livni took over Kadima following the stroke which incapacitated what party founder, who pushed \"unilateral disengagement\" as PM in the early 2000s?",
        "answer": "Ariel Sharon"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One of these particles was posited by Sheldon Glashow to solve the Cabibo theory. The discoverer of these particles named them after a nonsense word in Finnegans Wake and developed the SU(3) system for classifying them, which he called the Eightfold Way. For 10 points, name these building blocks of subatomic particles, discovered by Murray Gell-Mann.",
        "answer": "quarks"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A 1979 experiment in Hamburg confirmed the existence of what particles, which carry the color force between quarks?",
        "answer": "gluons"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A comic book series starring this character is where The Punisher first appeared. In the 1970s, this character was tormented by The Jackal creating clones of his loved ones, which provided the basis for a reviled 1990s \"Clone Saga\" storyline. For 10 points, name this Marvel character who opposes Dr. Octopus, The Lizard, and Venom and is the alter-ego of Peter Parker.",
        "answer": "Spider-Man"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Which singer, who sang about the Troubles in Northern Ireland in his band’s song Sunday, Bloody Sunday, wrote the music to the ill-fated Broadway musical about Spiderman?",
        "answer": [
          "Bono",
          "Paul Hewson,"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This character's British counterpart was a real person named Ruby Loftus, and her Canadian version was Ronnie the Bren Gun Girl. This character is distinct from the subject of the Howard Miller \"We Can Do It!\" poster, and was popularized by a Norman Rockwell painting. For 10 points, name this World War II poster character who promoted women's working in factories.",
        "answer": "Rosie the Riveter"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "American women also competed in a professional baseball league during the war, which ended up being the subject of what 1990’s film starring Geena Davis and Madonna?",
        "answer": "A League of Their Own"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "James Carleton launched a \"total war\" against this tribe, which was forced onto the \"Long Walk to Bosque Redondo\" by Kit Carson. In November 2014, this tribe's member Chester Nez died; Nez was the last surviving member of this tribe who worked as a \"code talker\" during World War II. For 10 points, name this large American Indian tribe in the Southwest.",
        "answer": "Navajo"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Navajo language has recently been shown to be distantly related to a group of languages spoken along the Yenisei River in what country?",
        "answer": "Russia"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Nancy Lopez was one of the most dominant athletes in this sport during the 1980’s, while former track star Babe Didrickson Zaharias also won numerous tournaments in this sport in the 1950’s. Se Ri Pak of South Korea achieved success in this sport at a young age, as did Michelle Wie, who competed in a series of events on the PGA tour. For 10 points, name this sport in which Annika Sörenstam made history in 2001 by shooting 59 in a competition round.",
        "answer": "golf"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Zaharias also won gold medals for the USA in track and field at the 1932 Olympics, which were held in which American city that also hosted the 1984 games?",
        "answer": "Los Angeles"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Brezhnev Doctrine was used to justify the invasion that ended this period of time. It began with its creator announcing “socialism with a human face.” Gustáv Husák replaced the leader who began this period, Alexander Dubček (DOOB-check), after the Warsaw Pact invasion deposed him. For 10 points, name this relaxing of one-party control in Czechoslovakia in 1968.",
        "answer": "Prague Spring"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What country led by Enver Hoxha left the Warsaw Pact over the decision to invade Czechoslovakia?",
        "answer": "Albania NHBB B 2014-2015"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "COLONIAL VIRGINIA",
      "prompt": "In pre-Revolutionary Virginia, who or what was the…",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country which chartered the Virginia Colony?",
          "answer": "England"
        },
        {
          "question": "Fort on a namesake river which was the first European settlement?",
          "answer": "Jamestown"
        },
        {
          "question": "Powhatan princess who saved John Smith's life?",
          "answer": "Pocahontas"
        },
        {
          "question": "Leader of a 1676 \"rebellion\" which burned the capital?",
          "answer": "Nathaniel Bacon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Governor targeted in that rebellion, who shares his name with the hometown of the University of California's oldest campus?",
          "answer": "William Berkeley"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ancestor of the Virginia General Assembly which functioned as the colonial legislature?",
          "answer": "House of Burgesses"
        },
        {
          "question": "College chartered in 1693, America's second-oldest after Harvard?",
          "answer": "College of William & Mary"
        },
        {
          "question": "Second governor of Virginia and namesake of another state?",
          "answer": "Baron De La Warr \"Delaware\""
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "AMERICAN IMMIGRANT GROUPS",
      "prompt": "Name the american immigrant groups...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "First fled to the British colonies when Louis XIV outlawed Huguenots?",
          "answer": "France"
        },
        {
          "question": "Founded the first pizza shop in the U.S. in 1905?",
          "answer": "Italy"
        },
        {
          "question": "Were subject to \"need not apply signs\" after emigrating during a potato famine?",
          "answer": "Ireland"
        },
        {
          "question": "Were the target of an \"exclusion act\" following their work on railroads in the West?",
          "answer": "China"
        },
        {
          "question": "Settled in Glendale and Fresno, California, after a Turkish genocide?",
          "answer": "Armenia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Brought tales of the Kalevala (KAH-leh-VAH-luh) to the Upper Peninsula of Michigan?",
          "answer": "Finland"
        },
        {
          "question": "Were the subject of the \"Gentleman's Agreement\" under Theodore Roosevelt?",
          "answer": "Japan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Include Jerry Seinfeld, Steve Jobs, and Paula Abdul and other Arab-Americans?",
          "answer": "Syria"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "ANGLO-SAXON ENGLAND",
      "prompt": "During England's Anglo-Saxon period, which...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "type of seafaring Scandinavian raiders often raided the coast?",
          "answer": "Vikings"
        },
        {
          "question": "king of Wessex was called \"the Great\"?",
          "answer": "Alfred the Great"
        },
        {
          "question": "1066 battle began William the Conqueror’s conquest of England?",
          "answer": "Battle of Hastings"
        },
        {
          "question": "language was used to compose the poem Beowulf?",
          "answer": "Old English"
        },
        {
          "question": "position, later held by Thomas Beckett, was created by the missionary Augustine?",
          "answer": "archbishop of Canterbury"
        },
        {
          "question": "nickname was given to King Aethelred after his defeat by Sweyn Forkbeard?",
          "answer": "unready"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"Venerable\" monk authored an Ecclesiastical History of the English People?",
          "answer": "The Venerable Bede"
        },
        {
          "question": "king was killed by Norman forces at the Battle of Hastings?",
          "answer": "Harold Godwinson"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This editor of the newspaper Iskra wrote about the “burning questions of our movement” in a pamphlet titled What Is to Be Done? As leader, he instituted the moderate New Economic Policy. He issued a series of (20 pts)",
        "“April Theses” after riding through Germany on a sealed train. This man, for whom (10 pts)",
        "St. Petersburg was renamed in 1924, brought his country out of World War I with the Treaty of Brest-Litovsk. For 10 points, name this leader of the Bolsheviks."
      ],
      "answer": "Vladimir Lenin"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A holder of this office feuded with a faction led by his rival Milo and engineered the exile of his enemy Cicero. Another holder of this office proposed the reforming Lex Sempronia Agraria and, like his brother, was killed by an Optimate (20 pts)",
        "mob. Publius Clodius Plucher and Gaius and Tiberius Gracchus all held this position, which was granted (10 pts)",
        "sacrosanctity and the power of the intercessio, or the veto. For 10 points, name this office of the Roman Republic, created to represent the plebeians."
      ],
      "answer": "tribunes"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man's campaign commercials, which were designed by Richard Wirthlin, included the \"bear in the woods ad\" advocating military preparedness. He asked \"are you better off now than you were four years ago?\" when he won the Presidency and was re-elected on the (20 pts)",
        "\"Morning in America\" campaign. This supporter of the Strategic Defense Initiative defeated (10 pts)",
        "Walter Mondale by a landslide in 1984. For 10 points, name this Republican President of the 1980s."
      ],
      "answer": "Ronald Wilson Reagan"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) An object aboard this vessel includes Blind Willie Johnson's recording of \"Dark Was the Night, Cold Was the Ground\" and the first Brandenburg Concerto, as well as greetings in fifty-five languages. This vessel, which holds a (20 pts)",
        "\"golden record\" compiled by Carl Sagan, was launched in 1977 and left the (10 pts)",
        "solar system in 2013. For 10 points, name this probe which is currently the farthest manmade object from Earth."
      ],
      "answer": "Voyager 1"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Governor William Lane forced the negotiation of this event, which was the high-water mark for William Marcy and other proponents of a southern route for the (20 pts)",
        "Transcontinental Railroad. This event resulted in a ten million dollar price being paid for the Mesilla Valley area. This event was negotiated by the American ambassador to (10 pts)",
        "Mexico, with Santa Anna. For 10 points, name this this 1853 land transfer of parts of Arizona and New Mexico to the United States."
      ],
      "answer": "Gadsden Purchase"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This program had a complex system of over three \"work classifications\" and targeted those with educational problems; eighty-nine percent of its participants had not graduated high school. This program, directed by Robert Fechner, sent the Indian Division to work on (20 pts)",
        "soil projects. This program employed three million people and planted three (10 pts)",
        "billion trees from 1933 to 1942. For 10 points, name this New Deal program in which men lived in camps and worked outdoors."
      ],
      "answer": "CCC"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This European power used the \"ten-cow rule\" to distinguish and privilege some colonial subjects. The Casement Report criticized the colonial policies of this European power, alleging that it cut the (20 pts)",
        "hands off unproductive rubber workers. This European power treated the Tutsis better than the Hutus in what became Rwanda, and ran a so-called (10 pts)",
        "\"Free State\" exploited by King Leopold II. For 10 points, name this European country which colonized most of the Congo."
      ],
      "answer": "Kingdom of Belgium"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man wrote about the execution of John Brown in “The Portent,” the first poem in his unpopular collection Battle-Pieces, and described his visit to the Middle East in Clarel. He described fraudsters on the Mississippi River in The (20 pts)",
        "Confidence Man, and created the characters of Stubb, Flask, and (10 pts)",
        "Starbuck in another novel. For 10 points, name this American author of nautical tales such as “Billy-Budd” and a novel set on the Pequod, Moby- Dick."
      ],
      "answer": "Herman Melville NHBB B 2014-2015"
    }
  ]
}